Biosphere.
Earth
is
the
only
known
place
that
has
ever
been
habitable
for
life.
Earth's
life
developed
in
Earth's
early
bodies
of
water
some
hundred
million
years
after
Earth
formed,
roughly
four
billion
years
ago.
Earth
provides
liquid
water—an
environment
where
complex
organic
molecules
can
assemble
and
interact,
sufficient
energy
to
sustain
a
metabolism.
Plants
and
other
organisms
take
up
nutrients
from
water,
soils
and
the
atmosphere.
These
nutrients
are
constantly
recycled
between
different
species.
Earth's
life
has
been
shaping
and
inhabiting
many
particular
ecosystems
on
Earth
and
has
eventually
expanded
globally
forming
an
overarching
biosphere.
Earth's
life
has
also
over
time
greatly
diversified,
allowing
the
biosphere
to
have
different
biomes,
which
are
inhabited
by
comparatively
similar
plants
and
animals.
The
different
biomes
developed
at
distinct
elevations
or
water
depths,
planetary
temperature
latitudes
and
on
land
also
with
different
humidity.
Earth's
species
diversity
and
biomass
reaches
a
peak
in
shallow
waters
and
with
forests,
particularly
in
equatorial,
warm
and
humid
conditions.
While
freezing
polar
regions
and
high
altitudes,
or
extremely
arid
areas
are
relatively
barren
of
plant
and
animal
life.
Therefore,
life
has
impacted
Earth,
significantly
altering
Earth's
atmosphere
and
surface
over
long
periods
of
time,
causing
changes
like
the
Great
Oxidation
Event.